<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<blockquote class="ballot-note" data-augury-generated="true" id="bn1">
  <p><b>Note to Balloters:</b> The substantive change in this ballot broadens how an operation identifies its target and its parameter types: <code>OperationDefinition.resource</code> and <code>OperationDefinition.parameter.type</code> are now typed as <code>uri</code> rather than <code>code</code>, so operations can be defined against logical models identified by a canonical URI, not only resource-type codes. The remaining OperationDefinition changes are narrative: escape-valve guidance for <code>kind</code> and <code>parameter.binding.strength</code>, a jurisdiction-status clarification, and editorial corrections.</p>
  <p><b>Compatible substantive</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>OperationDefinition.resource</code> retyped from <code>code</code> to <code>uri</code> so operations can target logical models identified by canonical URI [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-51651">FHIR-51651</a>]</li>
    <li><code>OperationDefinition.parameter.type</code> retyped from <code>code</code> to <code>uri</code> so a parameter can be typed against a logical model by URI [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-51651">FHIR-51651</a>]</li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Non-substantive</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Clarified handling for <code>OperationDefinition.kind</code> values outside the bound value set (escape-valve guidance) [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55176">FHIR-55176</a>]</li>
    <li>Clarified handling for <code>OperationDefinition.parameter.binding.strength</code> values outside the bound value set (escape-valve guidance) [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55178">FHIR-55178</a>]</li>
    <li>Jurisdiction elements are no longer deprecated but retain a clarifying deprecation note in the resource narrative [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53766">FHIR-53766</a>]</li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Technical correction</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Spelling and abbreviation corrections applied to the OperationDefinition narrative [<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55175">FHIR-55175</a>]</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The OperationDefinition resource provides a formal computable definition of an <a href="operations.html">operation</a> or <a href="search.html#advanced">a named query</a>.
The OperationDefinition serves two principal purposes:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>To allow for automatic determination of system compatibility</li>
 <li>To allow for dynamic generation of forms to drive the operations</li>
</ul>
<p>
See below for further information about these, and about how operations and named queries are executed.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
OperationDefinitions are published to define operations that servers can implement in a common fashion. 
The FHIR specification itself describes some (see below), and other organizations (including 
IHE, national programs, jurisdictions and vendors) are able to publish additional OperationDefinitions.
</p>
<p>
OperationDefinition resources are referred to from two different places:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>From a <a href="capabilitystatement.html">CapabilityStatement</a>, to declare what operations a system does or should implement</li>
 <li>From another OperationDefinition resource. This allows for a server to describe a limited implementation of a standard operation, or to allow traceability if the server has to rename the operation due to a name clash</li>
</ul>
<p>
OperationDefinitions can be used to define a custom query (kind = query, discussed below) which 
functions as a special kind of search. This is different to a SearchParameter because a custom query 
may define multiple parameters and can define of complex search behavior beyond what SearchParameter can specify. 
It also typically overrides the behavior of the query functionality, while search parameters can only act 
as additional filters.
</p>
</div>
</div>
